Guide to the Creative Time Records MSS.179
Fales Library and Special Collections
Creative Time Records
1974-2012, 2020-ongoing
Fales Library and Special Collections
Creative Time, Inc.
MSS.179
238.58 Linear Feet in 27 record cartons, 83 manuscript boxes, 15 oversized folders, 321 jewel cases, 2 card boxes, 9 oversized flat boxes, 2 tall manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, 22 box binders, 1 shared card box, 5 shared record cartons, 1 shared flat box, and 1 shared cassette box
32 U-matic
17 Betamax
30 Digital_Betacam
47 DVDs
234 DVD-R
3 Hi8
33 MiniDV
2 audiocassettes
19 CDs
43.3 Gigabytes in 1174 computer files
13 websites in 13 archived websites.
Founded in 1973, Creative Time is a public arts organization based in New York City. The organization has a history of commissioning, producing, and presenting public artworks worldwide. Three core values guide the organization's work: "art matters, artists' voices are important in shaping society, and public spaces are places for creative and free expression." The materials in this collection document all aspects of the creation, production, promotion, exhibition, and reception of commissioned artworks from 1974-2012, as well as their web presence starting in 2020. Notable projects in the collection include Tribute of Light, the two beacons of light that illuminated lower Manhattan for six months after 9/11 (2001-2002); Playing the Building by David Byrne (2008); and Wink by Takashi Murakami, among many others.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Creative Time in September 2006. An additional accession was donated in 2014. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2006.179 and 2014.179.
https://creativetime.org/tender-presence/, https://creativetime.org/waters-of-a-lower-register-ajh/, https://creativetime.org/tender-jill-magid/, https://www.instagram.com/creativetime/, and http://creativetime.org/comics-2020/ were initially selected as part of the NYC Arts Community COVID-19 Response Web Collection in May 2020-April 2022. The accesion numbers associated with these websites are 2021.031, 2022.031, and 2020.039. In October 2022, crawling of the seeds were discontinued in NYC Arts Community COVID-19 Response Web Collection. In October 2023, https://creativetime.org/ was added and the above websites were captured through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. The accession number associated with https://creativetime.org/ is 2023.055. In November 2023, https://reworlding.creativetime.org/, https://creativetimereports.tumblr.com/, https://creativetime.tumblr.com/, https://creativetimereports.org/, and https://hq.creativetime.org/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2023.065. In July 2024, https://summit.creativetime.org/ and https://cosmologyscape.com/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2024.027.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into four series; the series arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Exhibitions and Projects
Series II. Grants and Development
Series III. Administrative Materials
Series IV. Archived Websites
Series I is arranged chronologically. Series II is arranged first alphabetically by grant funder, then chronologically by fundraising event. Series III is mostly arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Historical Note
Founded in 1973, Creative Time is a nonprofit arts organization that supports the creation of innovative, site-specific works by professional artists for public presentation in vacant spaces of historical and architectural interest throughout New York City. Its history of commissioning, producing, and presenting adventurous public artworks of all disciplines began in the midst of a significant period in which artists were experimenting with new forms and media that moved their works out of galleries and museums and into the public realm. Programs sponsored by Creative Time include both the visual and performing arts and are designed to encourage a dialogue between the artist and the community.
Their earliest programs invigorated vacant storefronts as well as neglected public spaces such as the Great Hall of the Chamber of Commerce in Lower Manhattan and the arches of the Brooklyn Bridge Anchorage. From 1983-2001, Creative Time presented Art in the Anchorage for annual exhibitions of emerging creative practices in art, music, theater, and fashion until its closure in 2001 due to national security.
Creative Time gained early renown for initiating Art on the Beach on two acres of landfill known as Battery Park City, an area targeted for future residential and commercial development. From 1978-1985, this site became a laboratory for artists of all mediums to develop large scale works and collaborate, bringing together architects, sculptors, performers, and musicians. The success of Art on the Beach became a model for the presentation of temporary public art for other city governments and arts agencies.
Creative Time's Citywide program was inaugurated in 1989 and provided a forum for individual artists to control the presentation of their work in public places and for the public to have greater access to artists and their process. Presenting projects on billboards, landmark buildings, buses, deli cups, milk cartons, ATM machines, and the Internet, among numerous other venues, and encouraging artists to address timely issues such as the AIDS pandemic, domestic violence, and racial inequality, Creative Time broadened the definitions of both art and public space throughout the 1980s and 1990s.
From 1973-1986, Creative Time was under the leadership of Anita Contini and continued until Cee Scott Brown took over as director in 1987. Anne Pasternak stepped in as director in 1993 and continued in this position through the 2010s. Today, Creative Time continues to provide hundreds of emerging and established artists with opportunities to create new works that expand their practices and foster career growth. Creative Time's alumni community includes Laurie Anderson, Beth B., David Byrne, Guillermo Gómez-Peña, Felix Gonzalez-Torres, Red Grooms, Jenny Holzer, Marcos Kurtycz, Takashi Murakami, Shirin Neshat, and Elizabeth Streb, among thousands more. Creative Time has remained committed to promoting collaboration within the creative community, frequently partnering with institutions like the The Kitchen, Lincoln Center, Lower Manhattan Cultural Council, MTA Arts for Transit, and the New York City Department of Cultural Affairs.
References:
1. Creative Time website, creativetime.org, Creative Time, Inc. copyright 1974-2008.
2. Unknown author, untitled Creative Time press document, unpublished, circa 1985.
3. Creative Time: 20 years of art in unexpected places.
4. Pasternak, Anne and Ruth A. Peltason, ed. Creative Time: The Book, 33 Years of Public Art in New York City (New York: Princeton Architectural Press, 2007).
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Some audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
A.I.R. Gallery Archive (MSS.184)
Jay Blotcher Papers (MSS.137)
Fashion Moda Archive (MSS.091)
Judson Memorial Church Archive (MSS.094)
Mabou Mines Archive (MSS.133)
REPOhistory Archive (MSS.113)
Harold and Joyce Pomeroy Schwartz Public Art Archive (MSS.171)
Martha Wilson Papers (MSS.175)
David Wojnarowicz Papers (MSS.092)
Scope and Contents
The Creative Time Records (1974-2012, 2020-ongoing) contains materials that document the organization's commitment to, and history of, commissioning, producing, and presenting public artworks of all disciplines, both nationally and internationally. The bulk of the collection consists of exhibition and project materials from the organization's inception in 1974 through 2012. These materials include extensive production and promotional materials (such as artists' CVs and biographies; blueprints; site and installation photographs; slides, photographs of artists' work in print and digital formats; exhibition catalogs, postcards, and invitations; exhibition reviews; and accepted proposals for Creative Time sponsored projects such as Art at the Anchorage and Citywide) that document all aspects of the creation, exhibition, and reception of the commissioned artworks and projects. Additionally, since many of the projects and exhibitions took place in New York, they reflect the organization's influence on the landscape (as in the rehabilitation of public spaces such as the Great Hall of the Chamber of Commerce in Lower Manhattan and the arches of the Brooklyn Bridge Anchorage). The collection also includes grant and fundraising materials (applications, reports, and fundraising campaign documents such as mailings and invitations to benefits) that reflect how the organization has financially supported its mission. Lastly, there is administrative material (general correspondence, certificates, art education program documentation, materials related to conference and symposia participation, and materials on the organization's possible merger with another art organization) that reflects the organization's growth. The collection also includes archived websites related to Creative Time and their commissioned projects first captured in 2020.
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Acetate film; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Minutes (administrative records); Urban transportation.; Public art spaces.; Color slides.; Color photographs.; Calendars.; Catalogs.; blueprints (reprographic copies); Artists -- New York (State) -- New York -- Political activity; Art -- Finance; Art patronage -- New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.).; Artists -- New York (N.Y.); Grant proposals.; Art and state.; Art patronage.; Public architecture.; Public art -- New York (N.Y.); Political activists.; Politics in art.; Performance art -- New York (State) -- New York -- Exhibitions.; Performance artists.; Modern dance -- New York (N.Y.); Modern dance -- United States; Installations (Art) -- United States.; Local transit.; Experimental theater -- New York (N.Y.); Family violence -- Prevention; Alternative spaces (Arts facilities); Correspondence.; AIDS activists -- New York (N.Y.); Poetry.; Art -- Political aspects.; Art -- Exhibitions.; Art, American -- New York (State) -- New York -- 21st century; Art, Modern -- United States -- 20th century -- Exhibitions; AIDS (Disease) -- Social aspects -- New York (N.Y.); Financial records; Design drawings.; Minorities in art.; Ground plans.; Announcements.; Press releases.; Advertisements; Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.); Black-and-white photographs.; Negatives (photographic); Art, American -- New York (State) -- 20th century.; Art -- Exhibitions -- New York (N.Y.); Manuscripts for publication.; Posters.; Audiotapes.; Transparencies.; Schematic drawings.; Contact sheets.; Programs (documents); Videocassettes.; Reviews (document genre); Clippings (information artifacts); News web sites -- United States.; Creative Time, Inc.; Anderson, Laurie, 1947-; B., Beth; Brown, Cee; Byrne, David, 1952-; Contini, Anita; Gómez-Peña, Guillermo; Gonzalez-Torres, Félix, 1957-1996; Grooms, Red; Holzer, Jenny, 1950-; Kitchen Center for Video, Music, Dance, Performance, Film, and Literature (New York, N.Y.); Kurtycz, Marcos; Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts; Lower Manhattan Cultural Council; National Endowment for the Arts; Neshat, Shirin, 1957-; New York (N.Y.). Department of Cultural Affairs; Pasternak, Anne, 1964-; Streb, Elizabeth
- Series I: Exhibitions and Projects, 1974-2012; 204.08 Linear Feet in 19 record cartons, 75 manuscript boxes, 275 jewel cases, 22 box binders, 8 oversized flat boxes, 9 oversized folders, 5 shared record cartons, 2 tall manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 shared flat box, and 1 shared cassette box; 43.1 Gigabytes in 1166 computer files; 28 U-matic; 17 Betamax; 30 Digital_Betacam; 44 DVDs; 211 DVD-R; 26 MiniDV; 2 audiocassettes
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically by year of production.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of production and promotional materials for the various commissioned exhibitions and projects supported by Creative Time. These materials include artists' information (CVs, slides/videos/photographs, and artists' statements); blueprints; rental contracts; permits; correspondence; proposals; exhibition catalogs, brochures, and invitations to openings; site photographs; installation photographs; budgets; reviews; press releases; promotional items (hats, T-shirts, and cups); digital images and videos (mockups for exhibitions, images of final exhibitions and installations, and test runs and tours of installations), and mailed objects created by artist Marcos Kurtycz. Additionally, samples of artists' earlier or later work are included, most likely sent as part of their proposal packages. Also included are unrealized projects and in a few cases, exhibitions or projects not supported by Creative Time. The vast size of the production materials for each exhibition depicts the complexities involved in commissioning public art projects and the variety of locations, both national and international, selected for exhibitions.
  - Crafts in Action by Multiple Artists, February-March 1974
    - Correspondence and Programs (Box 1, Folder 1-2, Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Negatives, Contacts Sheets, and Prints (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
    - Slides (Box 110, Folder Sleeves 1-2)
  - Sail by Multiple Artists (Co-Presented by Orient Overseas Associates), December 1974-February 1975
    - Correspondence and Programs (Box 1, Folder 3, Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Prints (Box 14, Folder 4-6)
    - Slides (Box 110, Folder Sleeves 3-7)
  - Ruckus Manhattan by Multiple Artists, November 1975-January 1976
    - Correspondence, Programs, and Posters (Box 1, Folder 5-6, Box 34, Folder 3, Box 99, Folder 1)
    - Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Prints (Box 14, Folder 7-9)
    - Slides (Box 110, Folder Sleeves 8-12)
    - Big Apple Minute -- Access Copy (Box 147, Dvd 179.0312)
    - Big Apple Minute -- Original (Box 24, Folder ID: 179.0311)
  - New York Sky Events by Otto Piene and Alejandro Sina -- East Harlem and Central Park, June 1976
    - Flyers, Programs, and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 7-8, Box 34, Folder 18-21)
    - "Neon Rainbow" -- Negatives and Prints (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Anemones: An Air Aquarium by Otto Piene, October-December 1976
    - Flyers, Programs, and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9-10, Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Prints (Box 15, Folder 3-5)
    - Slides (Box 110, Folder Sleeves 13-17)
  - Round: Sound for Concave Surfaces by Max Neuhaus -- US Custom House, November 1976
    - Programs and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 11, Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Negatives and Contact Sheets (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
  - Custom and Culture 1 by Multiple Artists -- US Custom House, June-September 1977
    - Programs and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 12, Box 34, Folder 7)
    - Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Prints (Box 15, Folder 8-10)
    - Slides (Box 110, Folder Sleeves 22-25, 36-38)
  - Butler's Lives of the Saints by Ann Wilson, December 1977-January 1978
    - Programs and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 13, Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Negatives and Prints (Box 15, Folder 11-12)
    - Slides (Box 110, Folder Sleeves 26-28)
    - Audio Recording (Box 32, Reel 179.0699)
  - Downtown Drive-In by Multiple Artists, July 1978
    - Programs (Box 1, Folder 16, Box 34, Folder 9)
    - Prints (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Art on the Beach 1 by Multiple Artists -- Battery Park City Landfill, August-September 1978
    - Electronic Records, cuid40859
    - Programs, Correspondence, Flyers, and Schedules (Box 1, Folder 17-18, Box 34, Folder 10)
    - Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Prints (Box 16, Folder 2-4)
    - Slides (Box 110, Folder Sleeves 29-35)
    - Poster (Flat-file-folder 3 Right)
    - Aerial Video by Joe Kos -- Access Copy (Box 147, Dvd 179.0324)
    - Video Recording -- Access Copy (Box Shared Fales 146, Dvd 179.0726)
    - Video Recording -- Access Copy (Box 151, Dvd 179.0711)
    - Video Recording by Joe Kos -- Access Copy (Box 147, Dvd 179.0278)
    - Video Recording -- Access Copy (Box 151, Dvd 179.0699)
    - Aerial Video by Joe Kos -- Access Copy (Box Shared Fales 146, Dvd 179.0717)
    - Aerial Video by Joe Kos -- Original (Box 24, Folder ID: 179.0323)
    - Video by Joe Kos -- Original (Box 25, Folder 179.0277)
  - Art on the Beach Retrospective Program by Creative Time, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Custom and Culture 2 by Multiple Artists -- US Custom House, May-June 1979
    - Programs, Correspondence, and Flyers (Box 1, Folder 20, Box 34, Folder 11)
    - Photographs (Box 22, Folder 286)
    - Video Recording -- Original -- Jim Pomeroy (Box 32, Folder ID: 179.0695)
    - Video Recording -- Original --Kenneth Rinker and Dancers (Box 32, Folder ID: 179.0694)
    - Video Recording -- Original -- Stuart Sherman (June 8) and Laurie Anderson and Peter Gordon (June 14) (Box 32, Folder ID: 179.0696)
  - Downtown Drive-In 2 by Multiple Artists, August 1979
    - Flyers and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 21, Box 34, Folder 12)
    - Prints (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - New York: Art on the Road Poster Participant, October 1979 (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - The Artist at Work in America -- Hotel Vitosha, Sofia, Bulgaria -- Prints, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Press -- General, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Mail Art and Performances by Marcos Kurtycz, 1979-1989
    - Mira, Fuegomar, Zero Village, 1979-1989 (Box 20, Folder 1-15)
    - Do You Know Hockers Tablecloth (Box 23)
  - Art on the Beach 2 by Multiple Artists -- Battery Park City Landfill, September 1980
    - Electronic Records, cuid40860
    - Correspondence, Flyers, Programs, and Schedules (Box 1, Folder 25, Box 34, Folder 14)
    - Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Prints (Box 16, Folder 6-8)
    - Slides (Box 111, Folder Sleeves 3-13)
    - Video Recording -- Access Copy-- "School of Hard Knocks" (Box 151, Dvd 179.0708)
    - Video Recording -- Access Copy -- "School of Hard Knocks" (Box Shared Fales 146, Dvd 179.0735)
  - Masstransiscope by Bill Brand -- Myrtle Street Subway Station, September 1980-1983
    - Programs and Correspondence (Box 142, Folder 1, Box 34, Folder 15)
    - Poster (Box 99, Folder 2)
    - Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Prints (Box 16, Folder 9-11)
    - Slides (Box 111, Folder Sleeves 1-2)
    - Video Recording -- Access Copy (Box Shared Fales 146, Dvd 179.0776)
  - Projects at the Precinct House: Breaking In by Multiple Artists, October-November 1980
    - Correspondence and Programs (Box 142, Folder 2, Box 34, Folder 16)
    - Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Prints (Box 137, Folder 1-3)
    - Slides (Box 111, Folder 14-18)
  - Art on the Beach Retrospective Program (1980-1982), 1984 (Box 142, Folder 4)
  - Projects at the Precinct House by Multiple Artists, March 1981
    - Correspondence and Programs (Box 142, Folder 5, Box 34, Folder 17)
    - Contact Sheets and Prints (Box 137, Folder 4-5)
    - Slides (Box 111, Folder Sleeves 29-31)
  - Windspun by Liz Phillips, May 1981
    - Programs and Correspondence (Box 142, Folder 6, Box 34, Folder 18)
    - Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Prints (Box 137, Folder 6-8)
    - Video Recording -- Original -- Liz Phillips -- Installations Compilation, 1970-1999 (Box 30, Folder ID: 179.0675)
  - Art on the Beach 3 by Multiple Artists -- Battery Park City Landfill, June-September 1981
    - Correspondence and Programs (Box 142, Folder 7, Box 34, Folder 19)
    - Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Prints (Box 137, Folder 9-11)
    - Slides (Box 111, Folder Sleeves 19-28)
  - Ruckus Manhattan Revival by Multiple Artists, December 1981- March 1982
    - Programs, Correspondence, and Press (Box 142, Folder 8-9, Box 34, Folder 20, Box 21, Folder 258)
    - Slides (Box 112, Folder Sleeves 1-4)
  - Press -- General, 1981 (Box 142, Folder 10)
  - Principles in Perspective by Connie Beckley -- Chamber of Commerce, June-July 1982
    - Programs and Correspondence (Box 142, Folder 12, Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Negatives and Prints (Box 18, Folder 1-2, Box 22, Folder 287)
    - Slides (Box 112, Folder Sleeves 11-13)
  - Art on the Beach 4 by Multiple Artists -- Battery Park City Landfill, September 1982
    - Electronic Records -- Video, cuid40861
    - Correspondence, Press, and Programs (Box 142, Folder 13, Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Prints (Box 18, Folder 3-5, Box 22, Folder 288)
    - Slides (Box 112, Folder Sleeves 5-10)
    - Video Recording -- Access Copy -- Big Apple Minute -- Danny McCusker -- "Art in the Anchorage with Warhol" (Box 146, Dvd 179.0240)
    - Video Recording -- Access Copy -- Big Apple Minute -- "Centenary" (Box 151, Dvd 179.0690)
    - Video Recording -- Original -- Big Apple Minute -- Danny McCusker -- "Art in the Anchorage with Warhol" (Box 25, Folder ID: 179.0239)
  - Projects at the Chamber by Multiple Artists -- Chamber of Commerce, November-December 1982